[Music]
this very special version of 25-minute
physiology we're gonna be talking about
speed training and specifically the
difference between acceleration and
maximum velocity now I've been saying
this for years trust me it's all over
podcasts I've been doing since 2002 or
something that's a lie like 2012 I met
nonetheless but speed training in my
opinion is the most forgotten
misunderstood and just gets the least
amount of attention of all the possible
training adaptations I guess it just
doesn't sell 24-hour fitness memberships
or whatever it doesn't make you get any
likes on Instagram but this is the area
that actually is the most important for
performance athletes and I think is the
area that if you spend most of our time
in develop a skill set here you can
become a very valuable practitioner or
coach in any world right Eton MMA or
CrossFit or weightlifting speed is a
component to every bass guitar
performance so let's break down the two
different types of speed and then we'll
talk about in a second the different
ways I think that are best to train you
know I think the science thinks is the
best way to train for them so the first
part is acceleration and that's moving
yourself from a stop now some sports
like tennis are almost entirely
acceleration based so they're never
going to reach the opposite which is
maximum velocity or what I'll call
top-end velocity that typically is going
to take 15 to 30 meters of moving before
you can actually get to so think about
maximum velocity like a 200 meter dash
there's an acceleration phase for the
first again 20 or 30 meters depending on
the athlete and then from the rest its
top maximum velocity right what's the
highest mile per hour you can hit that's
what we're after
so sports like tennis will never have
that distance to cover so it's almost
acceleration the entire time it's
stopping it's restarting we're
constantly doing that sports like
basketball are still mostly acceleration
there are some spurts of like a 15 or 20
meter thing but when the courts only 60
feet or 90 feet long or whatever it is
we're just never really going to get to
Mexico I see that often other sports
like football some positions may see max
velocity imagine a wide receiver going
on a fly route or go around
but even still like an ax linebacker
runningback offensive lineman it's
almost entirely acceleration that
they're doing it's rare that they're
gonna sprint more than 20 or 30 straight
meters okay it's probably soccer though
it can be both and even a lot of top-end
velocity because they're covering big
distances of fairly uninterrupted
sprinting right maybe a little bit of
weaving and zagging but a lot of forward
sprinting so you know within
acceleration you may be thinking to
yourself what that's not exactly what I
thought acceleration was I like to split
it up into two different categories
change the direction and what we'll call
it Jilly okay now change the direction
is exactly like you're seeing the
picture which is sort of like a cone
drill or footwork drills things like
that the difference between that and
agility is choice reaction so this is
why a lot of coaches in this area will
get really irritated at people who do
fast foot drills and fun little things
on the beach or in the sand and think
they're training acceleration or agility
and it doesn't really do it that well
because you really know exactly where
you're stepping the problem with that is
is if very low likelihood it's going to
transfer to sport very much a hard part
about being a faster athlete on the
field is you have to not only be able to
move at that speed or change direction
like that but you gotta be able to do
that when you have decision-making and
when your foot isn't in the exact right
position this is why people tend to say
head what's called agility right which
is the image there right the app that
goes through the ladder as fast as you
can and at the end whether she brakes
right or left is dependent upon where
the app the coach throws the ball so
agility is a little more complex and
depending on your sport but most sports
are going to be more line upon agility
rather than just change of direction so
something like a t-test or a pro agility
test and it's not incredibly important
it's understanding say like a football
player but that's why I paint if I
combine the also do drills with the
athlete gets to run in a coach the coach
then points the direction they want to
see how quickly they can react when
their feet aren't set and how can they
get how quickly can they get to the
position all right so when it comes to
training them we have got two
predominant things we can do or major
approaches to it
most everyone is familiar with what's
called resistance training okay this is
really any time you're adding some
resistance to your body when we tend to
think about that we think about lifting
weights and barbells and dumbbells but
in the case of speed this typically
comes in things like dragging sleds or a
parachute or having a bungee pull you
may be doing vertical jumps on a mat or
the harness that's pulling you down to
the ground
could be even adding like a medicine
ball to a throw or a press or a jump
right it's adding mass to the system
that slows you down a little bit what
people don't necessarily talk a lot
about is the opposite which is letting
you go faster we tend to call this
assistant or over speed training now
this is interesting because if I told
you I want you to get faster why would
you do something that adds mass the
system that lets you or makes you slow
down why wouldn't you do something that
actually teaches you to go faster then
you possibly can now there's actually a
strong literature or scientific base
behind assistance training it turns out
it's incredibly effective the most
common example imagine doing sprint work
like you've seen the picture here where
you're pulling a sled or having a band
pull you and hold you back the
assistance version would be flipped
where you have the coach pull you
forward other ways you could do this say
your maximum running speed on the track
is 15 miles per hour well then maybe you
get on a treadmill and set it to 16 I
don't set it so much like 20-25 where
you can't even run your entire mechanics
or gaiter all screwed up you're just
trying not to fall on your face that's
not what we want to get we want just a
little bit help to help you learn to go
a little bit faster another example
where things like if you're swinging a
baseball bat that's 30 ounces practice
swinging a wool football bat that's 10
ounces learn to move it faster don't do
it so much again that it screws up the
mechanics of your swing but just a
little bit to where you learn to
actually go faster bands are affected
with this imagine doing vertical jumps
or instead of the band's are holding you
to the ground you have the band's pull
you up so if you can jump 30 inches in
the air normally the band lets you jump
35 now of
course if you pay attention to anything
I do I'm not going to tell you one
approach resistant or assisted it's
better than another for speed train they
pulled how pros and cons and this is one
case actually where the story is pretty
damn simple I'm going to keep you that
answer it's a second which one's better
for acceleration which one's better for
top-end velocity
I'm not gonna I'm not going to get
Street guilty you gotta think think
about acceleration and think about
resistance training for speed and think
about assistance training which of these
would probably improve acceleration the
most what's the problem with
acceleration what do you what's the
biggest hurdle you have to moving faster
with acceleration well think about max
velocity same thing which one of these
two approaches would be better for max
velocity and if you're critically
thinking about this it's actually nice
because the science supports what your
gut instincts would tell you do you
really think that dragging this sled
behind me where I'm going slower than I
can normally run would help me run at a
faster maximum velocity well turns out
it doesn't but it's actually really good
at teaching you to accelerate why
because a big part of acceleration is
overcoming inertia so learning to move
fast with a little bit of resistance is
actually really helpful for acceleration
you want to improve your top and
velocity though you need to incorporate
some assistance training learn to move
faster okay and again you can look
there's probably been 30 studies anymore
published in this area and if you look
at them collectively that's what it's
going to support both types of training
are good of course incorporate them both
I'm just saying think about the athlete
you're working with or the client you're
working with and think about the demands
of their sport are they more relying on
acceleration or velocity are they equal
are they 80% velocity 20% acceleration
or the inverse well then potentially
implement these different types of speed
training accordingly I'll give you one
really clear example my colleague Lee
Brown has done a tremendous
research in this area and probably his
most iconic study was a wiffle ball bat
study and what he did is he looked at
the baseball bat swing and you've all
seen the baseball players in the on-deck
circle they put the doughnut alright
that heavy circle on a baseball bat they
swing it a few times and it feels really
heavy take the doughnut off swing their
bat net feels lighter well it turns out
and only does that not work it actually
makes the baseball bat slower but if you
swing a wiffle ball bat which is light
plastic bat before you swing your
baseball bat although it makes it feel a
little bit heavier it actually lets you
swing the bat faster right now
psychology plays into this and again you
don't want to change the mechanics of
something really skill specific like a
baseball swing so I'm not saying make
all your baseball players do what
football bats I am saying think about it
from a conceptual level that don't
forget the over speed or the really fast
piece of training all right so hopefully
I've convinced you and again you can
look at the literature on that but I
want to jump to now is actually training
recommendations so I'm gonna go through
a couple of samples of things you could
do and we'll start with the acceleration
piece now one of my favorite is called
dynamic variable resistance or what some
would call compensatory acceleration now
the powerlifting community gets that
gets the win for this one they really
popularized it I'm not sure who invented
it who knows but they definitely pop
your eyes dit it's not invented it and
I'm gonna show you some videos of
exactly what that looks like in a second
but what's actually kind of happening
here is you can see the gentleman
squatting and chest this side Ryan maybe
you can try to highlight that there are
black bands attached to the barbell okay
now the band's if you think about a
rubber band these are not like your
thera-band unlike little ones these are
really heavy thick bands that at the end
when they're stretched to the maximum
are gonna add a hundred maybe more
pounds of force to it so you attach the
bands above attach them to the barbell
and ice you squat down the bands get
really tight and they're pulling on the
barbell so as you squat down below what
starts happening then lower lower you go
the more and more floors come from the
Behrend which means the less and less
force is required for
you know to move the barbell up okay so
imagine there's 500 pounds in the bar he
squats down at the very very bottom
maybe instead of feeling like 500 it
feels like 400 because the bands are
adding a hundred pounds of help because
they want to pull up as well but as he
stands up the bands get less tight and
less tightness tight so they add less
help to the bar so it's actually 500
pounds of the bar it feels like 400 the
bottom as he stands up but starts
feeling like 424 50 480 and then to get
to the top he actually has to put 500
pounds of force into that barbell to get
it up you know any of you that have a
strong background of physics or
biomechanics like don't kill me on the
exactly here think of the concept but
this is what happens and this is why I'm
talking about this in a speed video this
type of training our laboratory has
showed it and several others are a few
others have as well but it's not studied
incredibly well needs won't work but the
evidence that's there is pretty clear as
well as the training and the anecdote
that we've got from a lot of coaches
which is equally important okay but what
it shows is this as you go to move up
because the load on your back it's
actually kind of heavier and heavier so
the demand for the mass go up unlike a
normal squat where if it's 500 on your
back it's 500 back at the bottom it's
500 any place here it's not it gets
lighter as you go lower and heavier as
you stand up in order to then move out
of normal speed you actually have to
accelerate the whole time if you don't
you're gonna get collapsed by the
increase in force production and you
won't be able to move the bar so take a
look at the video maybe that'll explain
a little bit more so again the app that
goes down at the bottom and it's feeling
a little light at the hole but as he
stands up it gets heavier and heavier
and heavier so he's again having to
exert more force or more acceleration as
he goes up you can see the bands they're
really clearly to continue to move the
bar that's why we call it compensatory
acceleration you have to compensate for
the increase in weight by accelerating
through it okay now it's not exactly the
physics but
you get the idea it's also what's called
dynamic variable resistance because
unlike a normal squat where the
resistance is 500 the whole way in this
case the resistance is variable it
changes throughout the range of motion
depending on where you're at okay now
another example you can see here same
thing but instead of having the band
coming from the top to the bottom it's
coming from the ground up but the same
exact thing happens so as Chris goes to
stand up here the bands get tighter and
tighter and tighter so the weight is
heavier at the top than it is at the
bottom okay now there are some
differences between having the bands you
can do the same thing with chains if
people have ever seen people squat with
heavy chains same concept here okay and
you'll actually see Chris in a second
here do the same thing on a bench press
it maybe hopefully Ryan you can help me
out to the video isn't incredibly easy
to see but the band is attached to the
ground and you can see he's gonna do
some speed rip so get a good position
hold it and you'll kind of fire out five
or six reps and of course all of you
know as well by taking your shirt off or
at least cutting your sleeves off you
add twenty to thirty percent strength
and hypertrophy to your bench press so
make sure you try that tip as well all
right it's uncanny holds it down here
and then fires up a couple of speed so
he's not going for hypertrophy here he's
not going for fat loss he's he's trying
to build speed and power powerlifting
community crushed it with this did a
great job identifying how to implement
these things and the science is coming
through to support what they have
originally argued very good for
acceleration very good for power and a
little bit of speed development as well
now the other piece that I'll say to
committ story acceleration I believe
it's very good form a transfer to sport
perspective here's what I mean if you do
a normal benchpress when you get to the
end range of motion you actually have to
decelerate because if not the bar would
leave your hand but in sport that's a
terrible idea
imagine if you go to strike somebody in
a football game and you build up a lot
of force and acceleration and right as
you get closer you start to slow down
you'd be the worst player ever you can
you constantly lose every exchange you
want to actually accelerate through the
individual same thing if I'm punching an
opponent
if I'm doing a vertical jump I want to
have the most acceleration at the end
and go through contact but normal
resistance training actually teaches the
opposite to slow down at the end Remo
ssin by adding a band or a chain I don't
have to worry about that because it's
going to be the heaviest at the top so
I'm going to finish through the range of
motion
I'm gonna finish through the range of
motion or through the range of motion if
I'm dead the thing with there whatever
I'm doing so I really like that from a
conceptual model we don't have any
literature that suggests that makes
people better on the on the field that's
always a very hard thing to demonstrate
but it does show that it's more
effective for improving power and speed
I also think haffley's tend to feel
better because they feel that
acceleration through so I believe there
would be some support there although
again albeit no science per set so
that's compensatory acceleration I think
a very good tactic for acceleration
training giving you one tip here on the
maximum velocity I told you the over
speed or assisted stuff is a little bit
better for that so I'll show you a few
examples you can imagine instead of
pulling a sled you have some coach pull
you very very good there but here's a
video of somebody actually doing up with
the vertical jump so you see the harness
is pulling the athlete up in the air and
instead of being able to jump 30 inches
normally if that's his maximal height he
can now jump 35 or whatever happens to
be alright so again a lot of evidence
and a lot of research to support that
that's a pretty good training tactic so
hope you learned a little bit about
speed training today make sure to
comment below if you want more speed
training videos I haven't done a lot of
them I'm kind of kicking myself but this
is an area again I'm actually more
excited about that I purchased for your
trial offset this stuff doesn't jazz me
as much this stuff is much more
important for an athlete and a gap there
again ah you know why I do these videos
if you come to if you're in class come
to class with some next cost of some
questions we're gonna go do some of the
stuff outside anyways we've already done
it one of the two but Annie support is
always appreciated until next time we'll
see you
[Music]